welcome to meditating with john vervicky
we do this live stream every weekday
morning at 9 30 a.m
eastern time with monday's alternating
between a new lesson
darmadade a previous monday was uh
dharma day and a review of the whole
ecology and practices of paya day
at some point we will start alternating
in the upaya between reviewing
all of the eastern practices and
reviewing all of the western practices
if you're doing this for the first time
you're most welcome
what i suggest you do is to look for
links to
uh previous lessons and sits in the
description of this video
go immediately do lesson one keep
meeting with us
and review uh sorry continue to do a
lesson or two
every week in order to catch up with us
it might be a good idea also if you want
to uh partake in
in the uh what was a new course that
we've just started
together as a sangha for the wisdom of
hypatia if you review the lesson
that was given on monday although i'm
going to review it as well
today please like this
uh all of everyone please like this
stream to increase the
visibility of the utility algorithm so i
can help as many as people
many as many people as possible uh
uh with this practice um there's a lot
of value
that i would still like to share with
people uh thank you all for helping me
so much
for sharing all of the wisdom that we've
been able to draw from the buddhist and
the taoist
traditions but there's a lot of wisdom
that i want to share with people from
the epicurean stoic and neoplatonic
traditions
i think this is also very much needed at
this time
so please help me to help as many people
as possible
at the end of every session there's a q
a
period please limit the questions
at that time to questions from the
ecology of practice that i'm teaching
you
for more general questions uh please
come to the live stream
q a on youtube every third
friday of the month at 3 p.m eastern
time
and that will be the 21st of this month
okay so i'd like to do um a bit of
review
uh with you and then uh we will
chant and we'll set we'll open up the
time for some questions
so last time we talked about that the
central figure
uh from the western tradition the
touchstone figure so very much the way
the buddha was a touchstone figure for
us
right i wasn't trying to make anybody
into buddhists but nevertheless the
buddha served as a touchstone figure
an exemplar that we could use in order
to paradigmatically guide our way on the
path
socrates is the paradigmatic exemplar of
the western wisdom tradition
and socrates famously said the
unexamined life is not worth living
and then i mentioned that we should be
following mcclellan
that we should uh be making use a couple
of general practices right from the
beginning
that gives me also an opportunity to
remind you of the books so this is the
mandatory book
uh the wisdom of hypatia by mcclellan uh
please get that
and read uh up to the end of the first
degree of wisdom which is parts one and
two
and page seventy in the printed version
of the book
i strongly recommend for supplementary
reading
that you get here herdos what is ancient
philosophy
and then as soon as you can but we won't
be using it for a while uh arthur vs
lewis is the perennial philosophy which
is a
very good introductory text on
neoplatonism
and and its spiritual significance for
the western wisdom tradition
so mcconnell mentions that there should
be a couple practices you should be
doing one is regular self-examination
and so i strongly advise you to take up
the practice of journaling that he
mentions
some of you have already been doing that
in anticipation of some of the stuff
that's going to come with a stoicism
you've been uh journaling about your
cognitive biases
i recommend that you expand on that
um so what i typically do is at the end
of every day
as the clinical recommends i i i look
for things
that i admitted to that that so i look
for
uh vices of omission the things that i
could have done
uh that would have been more in line
with the cultivation of wisdom and that
i failed to do
and then you also look for vices of
commission
things that you did that
perhaps uh not only failed to cultivate
wisdom
but might have actively enhanced
patterns of self-deceptive
self-destructive behavior
and again remember the standard we're
using here
the standard is not a punitive
perfectionism
it is a virtuous friendship and then
that brings me to the third thing that
you note
without engaging in self-aggrandizement
you
note any instances of virtue remember
we've already been talking about this
there's an eastern version of this where
you celebrate the buddha
in this way you're celebrating right how
you are
inculcating the various virtues that you
are finding are central to wisdom
uh and the ancient tradition
uh that we're studying here recommends
of course four what are called the four
cultivar issues
moderation and i will teach you all of
these as we as we go on
and he's starting to teach you uh
courage
and and justice we'll talk about all
that
i will recommend as we get deeper into
neoplatonism that we
add in the virtues that were given to us
from the neoplatonic
christian tradition uh versions of agape
uh versions of faith and a version of
hope
uh again all of these um will be
tailored though so that they
are comported well uh with both stoicism
and um you know platonism so
please undertake those practices and
then the other one he calls it
commonplace
um that's fine um i've always used
i mentioned this on monday i i think of
it as maximization
this is the collection of maxims a good
source from that is of course the book
itself wisdom of high patient he gives
them
but a good source for you guys is also
lectio divina
when things stand out to you and you
resonate you might want to note them
down and the point of these maxims
is to memorize them as guiding
principles
and then we and then we engage in
maximization and i'm doing a play on
word here
because what i'm what i mean is and
we'll come back to this
when i'm trying to widen my frame
so that i'm considering the long term uh
nature of a particular pleasure a
particular desire i'm trying to fulfill
in pleasure i what i do is i apply the
maxim i've memorized the maximum and i
apply it in order to widen my frame
so that i have not just localized
attention on what's intense remember
when we talked about
hyperbolic discounting temporal
discounting and
we tend to confuse what is intense with
what's important
and we want to invert that we want to
become aware of what's important
and teach ourselves and train ourselves
to intensify that
this is a way of course of befriending
ourselves so
epicurus was uh you know you see that
each one of these traditions um and and
a fourth that i don't talk about here
but i'll talk about it after socrates
uh the skeptic tradition each one of
these traditions sort of they sort of
glum on to one uh
sort of an important feature of socrates
and then some uh
you know an important facet and then
some adjacent facets
um it's interesting to try and think
about trying to take all of these
different facets and then
work backwards to triangulate backwards
to what socrates
might have been what epicurus was deeply
impressed
with socrates um was socrates capacity
for anorexia
um and he thought this was also the
basis for socrates's wisdom and courage
and socrata and we'll see that each one
of these schools plays around with the
cardinal virtues
in a very very helpful manner
so anorexia is often translated as
tranquility um and that's
good uh but i bet
you we need to take much sort of a bunch
of english terms
and put them together as i suggested
last time there's tranquility
uh which is sort of a lack of tumult and
then
and these two two tubes are somewhat
synonymous but i'll stipulate a bit of a
difference here
there's serenity in the sense of a sort
of
right embeddedness in your world that
had that is conducive to inner
tranquility
and then there's equanimity that you're
not being
upset so adoraxia as i mentioned it
the a is a negation of inner tu tumult
inner turmoil inner conflict
and so epicurus was of the
like he proposed
that what we are most in need of
is anorexia and so he proposed that
what sets us most in turmoil is because
we are uneducated um about
our desires and our fears our desires
for certain pleasures
i think that's philosophically a little
bit inaccurate i think we desire
things that give us pleasure and we fear
things that give us pain
so all for simplicity cycle will just
allow
epicurus to speak the way he does okay
so we're desiring certain pleasurable
states uh we're fearing
certain uh painful states and we do that
in an uneducated manner
uh a similar proposal has been made
recently
by harry frankfurt the person who
did the work on bullshit um and
frankfurt
talks about the fact that we we can't be
wantons
uh that you know this is a an old word
it'll be
a wanton behavior it's just impulsive um
and we all know this we know we can't
act impulsive uh
but let's let's bring out a very
important maxim that's also an analogy
as the child is to the adult the adult
is to the sage
you as an adult know you should not be
as impulsive as a child
that you shouldn't be wanted because if
you are you're in turmoil and
self-contradiction and self-conflict
but what epicurus is asking you to
consider
is the possibility that there is a state
that
is comparatively much more mature less
impulsive and tranquil with respect to
your adulthood
that is analogous to how your adulthood
is more mature and less impulsive
to childhood and that is a very
promising proposal it's a very promising
proposal indeed
so what does uh epicurus recommend
well he recommends that we net we need
to engage in a process
of education uh and we and and
frankfurt goes even farther i think what
frankfurt does is helpful
he talks about uh process not just
education but of identification
what which desires do we identify with
which pleasures do we identify with
where do we are where are we setting
apart
interestingly enough that's what the
word believe originally meant it didn't
mean
to utter a proposition it meant to
believe in uh to set your heart upon
something
and this goes back to socrates notion
that
one of the things he did know is he knew
how what to care about and how to care
very well
how to care in a rationally uh profound
but spiritual but spiritually
efficacious manner
okay so what's the main maxim
governing the education process
the identification process we're trying
to
use rational reflection rational
discernment and here's where the
training in mindfulness is so beneficial
where the eastern and the western can
befriend and help each other we're
trying to use
rational discernment rational reflection
to give prioritization to the ease of
sustainability
we want to try and get to pleasures that
are the most
sustainable for us because those that
are most sustainable
are the ones that are least likely to
put us
into conflict they're the most
sustainable so that we can
we can use them as a basis as a
grounding for
our most sustained identity the
aspirational identity of who and what we
are most
aspiring to be so i think this is a very
very powerful
idea so what is the basic program well
the basic program is
when we get uh a desire
we step back and look at it and there's
there's the mindfulness moment right
and then of course there's also going to
be a looking through it but we step back
and look at it
and then we we catalog it we categorize
it and we use
a set of increasing uh we use a
set of criteria and they they should be
pursued in this order
in order to try and hone our
prioritization now this is not an
algorithm
you are going to have to bring your
judgment to play and
and that's partially as i'll say that's
why the savoring is so important
i'll come back to this okay so first of
all you ask
first of all you ask is the pleasure
physical or mental
right and epicurus argues that the
mental pleasures
are are more important because
they extend into the past and the future
or to use frankfurt's
terms uh they are are they have a
broader temporal scope with which we can
identify
you see one of the things that makes us
adults as opposed to children
and so notice i'm inverting something
that is normally talked about very
positively as it should be by the way
but now we're looking at the other side
of it as we always should
as well which is yes children are in the
present moment but children are also
wanton
and irresponsible at times which is
precisely why we engage
in the project of turning them into
adults
now that's because and this is really
interesting from psychology
right they lack a temporally extended
self
part of why people develop narrative
this is from cognitive science
his narrative allows us to develop an
autobiographical sense of self
a sense of self that extends into the
past
through the present and into the future
and that
that gives us a larger scope of
identification
and a larger scope of responsibility so
this is why adults
for example can feel guilty about things
they did five or six years ago
or they can aspire to be something that
they want to be
four or five years from now like going
to university and aspiring to get a
liberal arts education for example or
something like that
okay so you get priority to the mental
pleasures remember
this is not exclusive or punitive this
is
prioritization if you're in a situation
and
right there's just a physical pleasure
fine
but very often
and this is another maxim we we suffered
not because
we do evil but because we prefer a
lesser good to a greater good
so when there's a a clear choice
choose the mental pleasure but for both
the physical
and the mental pleasure you then ask is
it natural
meaning is it necessary for your
physical life
your mental life or your social life
so your physical life i'm not going to
talk too much about epicurus was very
impressed by the science of his day we
had a lot of good science
about that and that tells us what what
do we really need
right in order to sustain our physical
life not
to make to give it vitality what do we
need for mental vitality
well it looks like we need uh two things
with
two things uh which is right um
what's called sort of subjective uh
well-being i think we get that
uh by doing this practice so what i
suggest we
zero in on which is what epicurus zeroed
in on
is those things that are needed to
enhance meaning in life
the sense of connectedness to oneself to
others to the world
in a way in which we feel we are
connected to something greater than
ourselves that has a value
independent of our own egocentric
interests
and so that's meaning in life and so
those things that are needed for meaning
in life should be given priority does
that mean i exclude
any mental activity that not does not
directly give me meaning in life
no it's not exclusive it is not punitive
it's about prioritization but what it
does say is
if i'm doing something that isn't
directly needed for meaning in life
i ask myself what's the cost what's the
cost
how much turmoil is it
you know how much turmoil is it creating
in me
and so and then and again i can't tell
you what it is
i have to evaluate because it's going to
be different for different people it's
like well
this isn't you know this isn't natural
but when i pursue it it doesn't seem to
be causing over the long term
it doesn't seem to be causing lots of
turmoil okay so it's relatively safe
next we ask is it right
so is it natural and that as i
just said like is it something that's
needed directly
then when you're doing that as i just
said you ask is it necessary or
unnecessary
necessary means it's needed for meaning
in life or it's needed for physical
health
or it's needed for social health media
social life i should say
many of you are asking about that please
hold off on that because that's going to
come in when we talk about friendship
i know you're concerned about that but i
can't teach everything at once and i'm
going to address that when we come into
friendship
so is it natural right does it is it
directly within
uh you know constitutive of physical
life
mental life social life is it necessary
then is it short-term or long-term it's
short-term you always prefer the
long-term over the short term
how do you do that you do what's called
frame widening you have to open up and
identify with your future self
in the future world because this is how
you test to see
if the pleasure that you're seeking
has sustainability
that's where the maximization comes in
that's where you bring in the maxims
you have them ready to hand you memorize
them you call them up and they
tell you this so i gave you an example
one from socrates himself that i use
the unexamined life is not worth living
am i undertaking
a pleasure that long term will increase
my capacity to examine my life or
decrease my capacity
to examine my life that gives me a guide
that gives me a guide
okay now once you've done all that and
you have to
do those threes first before you do the
fourth you must do the three
is it natural is it necessary
is it long-term and then how easy
is it to obtain how much and this is
just a question of how complicated
of a problem-solving path you have to go
through to obtain it
how easy is it to obtain the general
idea is
ceteris paribus because remember the
other three are important
centers paribus you should go for those
that are easy to obtain
because they are much more likely to be
sustainable
and so then i gave you an example of a
practice that gets you
into exactly that which is the practice
of savory
where what we're trying to enjoy is the
purest pleasure of all
which i think is what anorexia is one of
my criticisms of how anorexia is
generally presented
in sort of academic world is it's
presented as a privation it's prevented
as a lack of pain
and this i think misrepresents what's
going on
for epicurus i would argue that the
adoraxia has a positive content to it
which is the pure pleasure of being
and so i recommend it to you the
practice of savoring the
practice in which you turn the world
into a garden and you're walking
you're walking around and you try to
have no sentences or scenes in your mind
you try to have your mind completely in
the world
and what you're doing is you're opening
up perception you're allowing
more and more sensations and details and
features
uh to flood in but at the same time
almost like
sherlock holmes you're increasing what's
called the down
so that's bottom up the top-down
pre-henship you're trying to notice more
patterns
as many patterns you know symptomatic
patterns different
you know almost like themes that are
are emerging in your awareness in in
synchronicities like in the union sense
between
an inner and outer felt sense of the
meaning of things
or or almost synesthetic almost like
you're
you're touching what you're seeing and
you're and
you're hearing colors uh and we know
that mindfulness
enhances the capacity for synesthesia
what you're doing there is what we
talked about from rusin
you're you're really appreciating in the
sense of musical appreciation
you're appreciating the musicality
of intelligibility you're appreciating
the musicality
of how right of how everything is
presencing
how everything how the moreness of
everything is coming into its suchness
and all these patterns
are like flowing the flowing music of
being
and you're noticing texture gradients
and you're noticing the
difference it you know tempo changing
emotional tone
and here's where all of the stuff you
did in rooting i'm learning to flow
soft vigilance you can bring it to bear
and you will get into
a a a a kind of flow state
that is just an enacted celebration
of what it is to joyfully
be that savoring
is designed to act as a phenomenological
a felt sense touchstone for you because
you can go oh
this is right this
is a sustainable long-term
pleasure that takes me into the heart
the ground of my being the very ground
of what i can identify with
and so you use that in a bottom-up
fashion when you're evaluating your
desires
you ask yourself well this is
tranquility
is my desire moving me towards that or
away from that so you use
the the save ring as a bottom up you
know
touchstone a felt sense and then you use
the maximization as a top-down
conceptualization to help you hone in on
whether or not you should pursue this
desire
okay and on friday we will we'll start
expanding on this when we
turn to how we deal with fear
okay everyone so that was a very long
review but i promise to do it i hope you
find it helpful
uh we're going to sit i'm going to
change what i already told them are
adjacent so i'm going to speak it aloud
so they know we're going to have a short
sit now
so we can get to at least a couple of
questions um remember we go longer on
monday wednesdays and fridays
we're going to have a 10 minute sit
we're going to have a 10 minute set
so everybody let's uh please get ready
get into position uh set your phones on
do not disturb
and we will begin when i say begin
we'll chat first and then go into a
silent set
let's begin
[Music]
oh
[Laughter]
[Music]
um
begin your silence
so
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communicates
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
so we're going to have some time for
questions we're going to try and set up
a bit of a schedule for questions
we're going to give priority not
exclusion but priority on monday
wednesday friday
uh to questions from the western wisdom
tradition the wisdom of hypatia
and then tuesdays and thursdays we will
give priority to
questions uh from the eastern tradition
that i've already taught you
please share observations and comments
as well as questions
and remember that we will therefore be
going a little bit longer as well on
monday wednesdays and fridays
oh here's some questions so raha yonas i
appreciate the value of priority
prioritizing being at ease because we
want to get out of this ease
i'm just adding that in as a comment
however i can't resist being a bit
worried about losing a certain level of
arousal
in the long run so i understand what you
mean and
uh that's why i i'm um
i'm trying to uh bring in
an aspect of flow uh in the savory
uh because what you're trying to do with
flow and i'll talk a bit more about this
on friday when i talk about the tulik
and the peritonic states
um you're in a state that in one sense
is fairly high
arousal uh metabolically
but nevertheless there's also that sense
of grace and ease in it it sounds
paradoxical i know
but that is one of the defining features
of the flow state and the savoring is of
course a kind of flow state
and so i think it actually um addresses
your concern
while still maintaining and we know that
we get our optimal performance
in the flow state so i think it
addresses your concern
while still maintaining our allegiance
to the epicurean
maxim that we should be seeking adoraxia
we should be seeking that state
of ease which doesn't necessarily mean
slowness right um
it could be it means but that sense
of it it can mean it doesn't exclusively
mean this
but because it can mean contented
contentment because when we talk about
it
that the the anorexia for the telic is
contentment
but the anorexia for the peritolic is
something like flow and engagement
and so i'm gonna i'm gonna talk about
that on friday
i'm gonna keep refining this for you
guys and so there is a
form of anorexia that's more more
peritolic more flowing
and and so the tranquility in there is
that is that sense of grace
uh even though you might be
metabolically in a very high state of
arousal
so we're going to come back to that i
promise on friday but that's to give you
a little bit of foreshadowing
uh kelly meyer says observation i have a
better problem with adding more and more
daily practice i already aspire to do
more than i have time for every day
the challenge is to become disciplined
us to do only those things
i'm trying to journal every day for
years so a practice that relies on that
habit
probably doomed for me uh okay so
don't rely then so much on on the
journaling
uh right now um and
and telling that this is but what's
difficult because
this is the pluralistic element of the
ecology of practices
again this
it is not expected that you do all
everything i'm teaching
and unless i i i'm going to be doing
some work with mark
soon and try to schematize how you
design your
a ecology way of thinking about it
initially is you have to find what what
takes for you
try things on for a few weeks see if
they take
um and they and try it at different
times in your life because
certain practices just don't take at a
certain part of your life i've mentioned
that i just tried
all the dream yoga stuff and it just
wouldn't take for me maybe
when i'm older it'll take i don't know
so
you have to do that and then you have to
also not only do they take
that's sort of a subjective side there's
an objective side too which is
how well do they actually address a
perennial problem
how well do they help you overcome
self-deception how well do they and
which kind of self-deception maybe
egocentric self-deception
maybe biasing self-deception right
that sort of thing and so you have to go
so think about how things evolve things
about how think about how things evolve
this is how your relevance realization
machinery actually works
this is how children actually learn
something so
like when things evolve like
you get variation in the species and
then you
and then there's selective pressure that
chooses the ones that are most
appropriate
in in the the current situation when
children are learning
a new strategy or skill they don't just
stick with what they first get the first
the first you know uh the first sort of
sequence of operations that works for
them they create a variation
and then they put selective pressure on
it and then they choose it so
what i'm giving you hopefully
is the variation of all the practices
and then
i'm increasingly trying to also give you
a sense a sense of how you select
for them and we'll talk more and more
about this and this is how you're going
to evolve
your ecology of practices i can't give
it to you
i would be suspicious of anybody who did
but i can give you our universal
principles by which you can evolve
in the ecology but it is ultimately up
to you because
you right i'm talking about
this applies to me but i'm directing it
too you are the author of your
self-deception
nobody else can ultimately solve that
this is why you have to ultimately
defend yourself right
so i can i can present you with the
variation
sort of the set of practices and
universal principles of selection
but you have to evolve your ecology
and because it has to it has to
fit your patterns of self-deception and
also
your patterns of aspiration only you
can relate to your future self and its
fire
i can't do that for you only you can do
that identification so
i'm not i'm i'm not trying to cop out
i'm going to try and give you
everything i can but what i'm trying to
get you to understand
is that you should be thinking about
cycling you cycle through a period where
you're varying and introducing new
practices
and then you compress them down you
select you get those ones that fit you
and fit together and fit you to the path
and you keep
cycling and you evolve your ecology
okay everyone thank you so much for
joining uh these classes
are deeply enriching to me uh
my techno friend and your my techno mage
and your friend he's also my technical
friend
my good friend and techno major mar was
back with us today
oh so thank you very much my beloved son
jason was there
uh doing all of his apprentice techno
maging in the background
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video
you'll also find links to the lecture
series awakening from the meaning crisis
uh to the dialogue series voices with
raviki to the upcoming series the one of
consciousness
untangling the world not and down the
road the one on the nature of the self
and the god beyond god and the
reinventing
please follow me on twitter it's not
against any of your principles for
the best updates about all of these
streams of everything that's
happening and talks that i'm giving if
you're interested in that invite others
who might benefit by sharing this series
please join the discord servers to chat
with others do the moving practices in
the group
i'll do group lectio to do an extra sit
and most importantly right now
where we will find a home for the group
practices that are so
central uh for the wisdom of hypatia of
course
reminder that we're doing this every
weekday morning at 9 30 eastern time
and i think that's everything please
remember that continuity of practice is
more important than your quantity
you are not holding yourself to a
standard of harsh perfectionism you're
holding yourself
to the standard of virtuous friendship
and boy is epicurus gonna be a helpful
one
as he helps us to get clear about what
virtuous friendship
is like when we talk about philosophical
companionships
there's no enemy worse than your own
mind and body
but as i was just saying a few minutes
earlier there's no friend no
ally no true companion on the path
greater than your old in my
own mind and body relax onto yourselves
and to each other
thank you everyone for your time and
attention
hey good care everyone see you tomorrow
you